http://youtu.be/kPnPCaDgz8A
http://youtu.be/kPnPCaDgz8A
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So let's take a look at another common
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Này hãy cùng đến với
system that we use.
những hệ đếm phổ biến khác.
There are other common bases.
Đây là những cơ số phổ biến khác.
Other common bases.
Rất phổ biến.
One of the more common systems that we use in computers is the hexadecimal
1 trong những hệ đếm phổ biến hơn cả, hay được dùng trong máy tính là hệ đếm
number system.
thập lục phân.
As the word connotes, we have a hexadecimal, which is a 6 and a 10,
Như tên của nó gợi ý, ta có thập lục, là 6 và 10,
which is a base 16 number system.
hệ đếm cơ số 16.
Again, the base is 16 and our valid coefficients are 0, 1, 2, up to 9.
Trong hệ đếm này, cơ số là 16 và hệ số hợp lệ là 0, 1, 2, tới 9.
And the next value is 10, but to make sure that we don't confuse a 10, which
Giá trị kế tiếp là 10, nhưng để ta không nhầm với số 10 khác,
is a decimal number 10, with a hexadecimal entity, we represent 10 by
số 10 trong hệ thập phân, với hệ thập lục phân, ta đại diện số 10 bằng
A, 11 by B, C, D, E, and F. So, A is 10 and F is 15.
A, 11 bằng B, C, D, E và F. Cho nên A là 10, F là 15.
So, for example, we might write some number in hexadecimal, which is, let's
Ví dụ, ta viết vài số thập lục phân, như là
say, a five digit hexadecimal number, like this.
số thập lục phân 5 chữ số như này.
And sometimes, because we may not have the luxury of representing subscript
Và bởi vì ta không thể ghi chữ số nhỏ
on a machine, we use a more convenient alternative, which is, we represent
trên máy tính, ta dùng cách khác tiện hơn,
hexadecimal numbers by prefixing the number with a 0x, and hhhhh.
để đại diện số thập lục phân bằng cách viết chữ 0x trước số, và hhhhh.
So, this is a five digit hexadecimal number.
Vậy đây là số thập lục phân có 5 chữ số.
So, let's take a simple example.
Hãy nhìn 1 ví dụ đơn giản.
So, for example, if I have the number 0x2A9F, and I'm told that it
Nếu ta thấy số 0x2A9F
represents a number which is, again, equivalent to writing
thì nó tương đương với
2A9F to the base 16--
số 2A9F trong hệ cơ số 16.
So, from here onwards, 0x2A9F is the preferred representation.
Vậy từ đây cách viết 0x2A9F sẽ được dùng.
We notice that this, again, represents the coefficients 2, A, 9, and F.
Chú ý lần nữa, các hệ số là 2, A, 9 và F.
But remember that A is a 10 and F is a 15.
Nhưng nhớ là A là 10, và F là 15.
So, this represents 15.
Cho nên, nó là 15.
And, again, my place value is 16 to the 0, 9 times 16 to the 1, 10 times 16 to
Và lần nữa, giá trị vị trí là 16 mũ 0, 9 nhân 16 mũ 1, 10 nhân 16 mũ
the 2, and 2 times 16 to the 3.
2, và 2 nhân 16 mũ 3.
So, this number represents 8192 plus 256, times 10 which is 2560, plus 144 (9 times 16),
Vậy số này đại diện cho 8192 cộng 256 nhân 10, là 2560, cộng 144 (9 nhân 16),
plus 15 times 1, which is 15.
cộng 15 nhân 1, là 15.
So this represents the number 10911 to the base 10.
Vậy số này đại diện cho 10911 trong cơ số 10.
So we also, when we talk about hexadecimal, we sometimes simply refer
Khi nói về số thập lục phân, ta thường nói ngắn gọn là
to it as hex.
số hex.
So when people talk about hex numbers, they're really talking about numbers
Vậy khi nghe nói tới số hex, ta biết là đang nói tới những số
that are represented using the hexadecimal notation.
trong hệ đếm thập lục phân.
So hex is not just used for representing numbers, we can also use
Mà hex không chỉ đại diện cho con số, nó còn dùng
the hex notation, also used for addresses.
ký hiệu hex, cho địa chỉ
So when we say that the address of a particular item is such and such, we
Vậy khi ta nghe địa chỉ của thứ này là vầy là vầy, ta hiểu là
represent the address as hex.
địa chỉ đó được viết bằng số hex
So here's an example of an address in hex that we will look at on the ARM
1 ví dụ về địa chỉ bằng số hex là, nhìn vào
processor that we're going to be using.
vi xử lý ARM ta đang xài.
So that for example, when I say that the address is 0x2000001A, I'm saying
Ví dụ, ta thấy địa chỉ này là 0x2000001A
that this is an address, and as we will see, this represents 12345678
là địa chỉ, có 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
digits of hex.
chữ số hex
They can also be used to represent contents of registers or memory.
Nó cũng có thể dùng đại diện nội dung của thanh ghi hay bộ nhớ.
Now, we will look at what registers are, and what memory is at a
Bây giờ ta học những thanh ghi, bộ nhớ là gì
later time, but for example I can say the content of
sẽ để sau, nhưng ví dụ, tôi nói nội dung của
memory location is 0xA0.
bộ nhớ ở vị trí 0xA0.
Or I can say the content of register, let's say register R0, I can represent
Hoặc tôi nói giá trị của thanh ghi, ví dụ R0, tôi có thể đại diện
the content of register R0 as containing the value 0xFFFF1011.
giá trị của thanh ghi R0 là 0xFFFF1011.
So one of the convenient things about representing hex is that, as I said,
Cho nên thứ tiện lợi khi viết bằng số hex là
it alleviates the burden of having to represent binary
nó thay thế 1 đống số binary
numbers in their entirety.
bằng những số của nó cho ngắn gọn hơn.
In fact this number, which is 10911, if we were to express it in base 2, it
Thực sự, nếu bạn biểu diễn số 10911 ở cơ số 2
would look like this.
nó sẽ là
It would look like 1111, remember, all the digits are binary.
1111, nhớ là số binary.
0010 1010 1001 1111.
0010 1010 1001 1111.
Now, I didn't actually work this out in my head.
Tôi không thể nhớ nổi nhiều số như vậy.
There is a convenient way of figuring this out, and that is that when I look
Có 1 cách tiện hơn,
at the hexadecimal, because these two are in the same base, the F is a 15,
là xài số thập lục phân, bởi vì chúng tương đượng, F là 15,
which in binary is 1111.
binary là 1111.
A 9 is a 1001.
số 9 là 1001.
An A is a 1010, and a 2 is a 0010.
A là 1010, và 2 là 0010.
So this is a simple way of converting between forms.
Có 1 cách đơn giản để chuyển đổi giữa 2 hệ thống.
Now, notice it is much simpler to write it as 2A9F than to write this in
Dễ thấy rằng viết là 2A9F đơn giản hơn
its entirety in binary.
viết 1 đống số 0, 1.
So hex is a very convenient notation, which will be used
Số hex rất là tiện,
throughout this course.
nên sẽ được dùng xuyên suốt khoá học này.